<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A iustification of two points now in controversie with the Anabaptists concerning baptisme: the first is, that infants of Christians ought to be baptized, with grounds to prove it, and their objections answered. With a briefe answer to Master Tombes twelve doubtfull arguments against it in his exercitation about infants baptisme. Also a briefe answer to Captaine Hobsons five arguments in his falacy of infants baptisme, being (as he saith) that which should have beene disputed by him, and Mr. Knowles, and some others; against Mr. Calamy and Mr. Cranford. The second point is, that the sprinckling the baptized more agreeth with the minde of Christ then dipping or plunging in or under the water: with grounds to prove it, and a briefe auswer [sic] to what they have to say against it. / By T.B.</title>
            <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77753</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B534</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E316_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872827</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">125273</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77753)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 125273)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 52:E316[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A iustification of two points now in controversie with the Anabaptists concerning baptisme: the first is, that infants of Christians ought to be baptized, with grounds to prove it, and their objections answered. With a briefe answer to Master Tombes twelve doubtfull arguments against it in his exercitation about infants baptisme. Also a briefe answer to Captaine Hobsons five arguments in his falacy of infants baptisme, being (as he saith) that which should have beene disputed by him, and Mr. Knowles, and some others; against Mr. Calamy and Mr. Cranford. The second point is, that the sprinckling the baptized more agreeth with the minde of Christ then dipping or plunging in or under the water: with grounds to prove it, and a briefe auswer [sic] to what they have to say against it. / By T.B.</title>
                  <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Shepard at the Bible in Tower-street, and for WIlliam Ley at his shop in Pauls Church-yard neere Doctors Commons.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.B. = Thomas Bakewell.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 19th 1645"; the second 6 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tombes, John, 1603?-1676.</term>
               <term>Hobson, Paul. --  Fallacy of infants baptisme discovered.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:125273:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A IUSTIFICATION Of two Points now in Controverſie with the ANABAPTISTS Concerning Baptiſme: The firſt is, That Infants of Chriſtians ought to be Baptized, with grounds to prove it, and their Objections anſwered.</p>
            <p>With a briefe Anſwer to Maſter TOMBES twelve doubtfull Arguments againſt it in his Exercitation about Infants Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Alſo a briefe Anſwer to Captaine HOBSONS five Arguments in his falacy of Infants Baptiſme, being (as he ſaith) that which ſhould have beene diſputed by him, and Mr. <hi>Knowles,</hi> and ſome others; againſt Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cranford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Point is, That the Sprinckling the Baptized more agreeth with the minde of Chriſt then Dipping or Plunging in or under the Water: With grounds to prove it, and a briefe Anſwer to what they have to ſay againſt it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. 3.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Beloved, beleeve not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits whither they are of God, becauſe many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> John Downham.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> printed for <hi>Henry Sheperd</hi> at the Bible in Tower-ſtreet, and for <hi>William Ley</hi> at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard neere Doctors Commons. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:125273:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader, conſidering it ever was, and ſtill is the cuſtome of all Chriſtian Churches in the world to baptize their Infants, and to ſprinkle the Baptized; although it hath been long oppoſed by the Anabaptiſts, yet they never left it in any age; then although thoſe men have publiſhed many Books of late againſt it, and no Anſwer to them is yet come forth, which makes them ready to ſay with the King of <hi>Aſſyria, I have gathered all the earth, and there was none that moved the wing, or opened the mouth, or peeped forth againſt it, Iſaiah</hi> 10.14. Yet let not this little book be deſpiſed for the unworthineſſe of the Author, but read it till ſome more able hand ſhall move for thy better ſatisfaction; thou knoweſt not but God may ſomtimes hide things from the wiſe &amp; prudent, and reveale them to babes, becauſe it ſo pleaſeth him, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.21. <hi>Aquilla</hi> and his Wife tooke <hi>Apollo</hi> that was mighty in Scriptures, and ſhewed him the way of God more perfectly, <hi>Acts</hi> 18. <hi>Naaman</hi> hearkned to his Maid-ſervant, when ſhe told him of a Propher in Iſrael that would cure him of his Leproſie; and to the advice of another ſervant, to obſerve the Prophets directions, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5. Then look not on the Author, but weigh the matter and arguments in the balance of the Sanctuary, and if they hold weight give God the praiſe, and me thy prayers; and I ſhall remaine thine in all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duties to be commanded</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Bakewell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="point">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:125273:2"/>
            <head>The firſt Point in Controverſie with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> is, That Infants of Chriſtians ought to be Baptized: the grounds to prove it are theſe following.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, if Chriſt commanded, and his Apoſtles practiſed the Baptiſme of Infants, then it ought to be done; but Chriſt commanded to Baptize all Nations, whereof In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants are a part, Mat. 28.19. and the Apoſtles Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed whole Houſholds, whereof Infants are a part, Acts 16.15.33. 1 Cor. 1.16. therefore Infants of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to be baptized.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if Chriſtian Infants have the promiſe to be baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, then they ought to have the outward forme of Baptiſme; but the Holy Ghoſt is promiſed to Chriſtians and their children, Acts 2.38, 39. therefore their children ought to be baptized.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If Infants of Chriſtians be ſeparated from Turkes and Infidels by vertue of their Parents Baptiſme, then they ought to be Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; but Infants of Chriſtians have this marke of diſtinction, For now ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Your children are holy, 1 Cor. 7.14. that is, they have an outward ſanctification, being diſtinguiſhed from Infidels, for the viſible Church therefore they ought to be Baptized.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If Chriſt did admit Infants to come unto him, and blamed them that would keepe them backe, and giving this teſtimony of them, that thoſe little children which he had in his Armes did beleeve on him, and that they had a right to the Kingdome of Heaven, then they ought to be Baptized; But the firſt is true, Mat. 18.3.6.19.13.14. Mark 9.36.10.14.10. Luke 18.15.16. therefore Infants of Chriſtians ought to be Baptized.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If infants of Jewes were circumciſed, and Chriſt came not to take away that benefit from them, but to change it to a better and larger benefit, from Males alone to Males and Females, and from one Nation to all Nations, and from a painefull duty to an eaſie duty, then I ſay that Chriſtian infants ought to be Baptized as well as the Jewiſh infants were circumciſed; but Chriſt never repealed that Command, but did enlarge it to all Nations, Mat. 28.19. and to both men and women, Acts 8.12.16.15. therefore Chriſtian infants ought to be baptized.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, if the Apoſtles buſineſſe was onely to convert men of yeares from falſe religion to the Chriſtian Religion, before they did admit them
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:125273:3"/>to Baptiſme, and did not wait till they were converted, from the ſtate of corrupted nature to the ſtate of Grace, becauſe they knew no mans heart, having the firſt converſion they baptized many without the ſecond; then Chriſtian infants who have no falſ religion to be converted from, ought to be baptized, although they be not converted from the ſtate of corruption to the ſtate of Grace; but the Apoſtles onely required men to beleeve that Chriſt was the Sonne of God, the Eunuch beleeved this and was baptized, and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> beleeved this and was baptized, although ſtill in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bonds of iniquity, Acts 8.12.23.37. and many beleeved the Scripture, and the words of Jeſus, many beleeved in his name, yet Chriſt would not truſt them although they were his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, for he knew their hearts, and needed not that any ſhould teſtifie of them, yet thoſe went away from Chriſt and never returned to him, Joh. 2.23, 24.6.66. this ſhewes they had onely the firſt converſion, and not the ſecond; and Jewiſh infants were circumciſed, if the Parents was but of their Religion, never waiting for the childes converſion from corrupted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the ſtate of Grace, and Chriſtians have as much power to bring up their children in the Chriſtian Religion, as they had to bring them up in the Jewiſh Religion; then it is a cleare truth that Chriſtian infants ought to be baptized.</p>
            <div type="objections">
               <head>Their Objections are next to be anſwered.</head>
               <p>FIrſt they Object; If they muſt firſt be taught before they be Baptized, then infants may not be baptized; but the firſt is true, Mat. 28.19. <hi>ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond. <hi>I anſ.</hi> The teaching them to obſerve, and to doe all that is commanded in that place, followes both Preaching and Baptiſme that both may be obſerved; elſe it were to affirme that Chriſt would have one Ordinance to be obſerved and not the other, when as he ſaith, <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and doe whatſoever I have commanded you;</hi> ver. 19.20. And to ſay Teaching is firſt ſet downe is not much to the purpoſe; if it be, then <hi>John</hi> did Baptize in the Wilderneſſe, and then it is ſaid, he Preached the Baptiſme of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Mark 1.4. and Chriſt ſaith, A <hi>man muſt be borne of water, and then of the Spirit,</hi> Iohn 3.5. and <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>I baptize you with water, but he comes after that baptizeth with the holy Ghoſt,</hi> Mat. 3.11. but Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, To baptize infants is to baptize thoſe whom the Lord hath not apointed to be baptized; and yet he grants, that infants may be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with the holy Ghoſt, and might be baptized if they were knowne to us from that Text, Acts 10.47. But ſaith he, To baptize infants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt commands to Baptize all Nations is very faulty; Firſt in caſting away that reſtriction which Chriſt hath put. Secondly, in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that all men whatſoever are to be baptized, and ſo it is no priviledge to beleevers and their children, But as common to Infidels as to their children. <hi>I anſwer.</hi> Here he denies the command of Chriſt to be a Rule,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:125273:3"/>and would make a reſtriction where Chriſt makes none, and then he makes a falſe concluſion, as if he ever ſaid, or did intend to baptize the children of Infidels before their Parents be taught the Covenant, and ſo by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme were admitted into the Chriſtian Church, but yet in other places he ſaith himſelfe, that beleevers children have no priviledge above the children of Infidels, but becauſe he ſlights this generall command to all Nations, which includes all ſorts of Mankinde, becauſe he hath not a ſpeciall command for Infants onely, I may ſay to him as Chriſt ſaid to the Phariſees, when they ſaid, to ſweare by the Temple was nothing, but he that ſwore by the gold of it was a debtor; ſo the command to Baptize all Nations is nothing, unleſſe it were for infants onely, when as the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſanctifies the gold, Mat. 23.16.17. and the whole Nation includes infants, but he muſt have them Diſciples firſt, becauſe it was reported that Chriſt made and baptized Diſciples, John 4.2. when as he grants it to be a falſe report, therefore nothing can ſafely be drawne from it, but I ſhall give a further anſwer to this, and Captaine <hi>Hobſons</hi> third agreement together. Againe, ſuppoſe we grant that men of yeares, who are conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from falſe religions to the true Chriſtian Religion, that ſuch muſt be taught the Covenant, being capable of Teaching before they have the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of it given to them; thus it was with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and with many Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens when they were converted to the Jewes religion; but when they were admitted their infants had a right to it without any teaching going before; and when they were capable they taught them the Covenant as they were commanded, Deut. 4.10.13. and ſo they taught them the meaning of the Paſſeover, Exod. 12.26.27. then why may not Chriſtian infants be taught the Covenant after they have received the token of it as well as Jewiſh infants. Againe, as they were meere paſſives when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the token of the Covenant, ſo are our infants, the worke is done upon them therefore they may be baptized.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they Object, That if they muſt repent before they be baptized, then infants may not be baptized; but the firſt is true, Acts 2.38. <hi>ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond. <hi>I anſw.</hi> It is true in men of yeares that are converted from Heathens to the Chriſtian Religion, but it is neither required of Jewiſh infants before Circumciſion, nor of Chriſtian infants before Baptiſme; for as they Circumciſed their infants, ſo <hi>John</hi> baptized them before or unto repentance, Mat. 3.11. therefore Chriſtian infanta ought to be baptized; but what if the Saduces and Phariſees, and the bloody Murtherers of Chriſt be called upon to repent before either <hi>John,</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> will admit them to baptiſme, will it follow that infants of Chriſtians muſt doe ſo actually before they be admitted to Baptiſme? the one of theſe was a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vipers, having the leaven of falſe doctrine that muſt be purged out, Mat. 16.13. elſe like Vipers it would eate out the heart and life of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:125273:4"/>Chriſtian Religion, Mat. 3.7. and the other was the leaven of prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which like ſavage Beaſts would trample Religion under their feet, then this alſo muſt be purged out, 1 Cor. 5.7.13. then as both muſt be purged out, ſo they muſt be both kept out. But will it follow, that infants muſt repent of Murthers and Hereſies before they be admitted to Baptiſme, let them that would have them to repent of thoſe foule ſinnes prove them guilty of them, or elſe they are very unjuſt to debarre them of the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Church, and actually Excommunicate them without any tryall or juſt proofe againſt them, and till then we muſt hold that they ought to be baptized.</p>
               <p>Thirdly they Object, If none muſt be Baptized but ſuch as are called, then Infants of Chriſtians may not be Baptized. But the firſt is true, Act 1.39. <hi>ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond. <hi>I Anſw.</hi> It is true, to thoſe afarre off, they muſt be called to the Chriſtian Religion, but it is not true to Chriſtians alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy called, nor required of their Infants any more then it was of Jewiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, for by vertue of their call their Children are holy, 1 Cor. 7.14. and ought to be baptiſed.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, they Object, That if none muſt be baptized but thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their ſinnes, then Infants muſt not be baptized. But the firſt is true, Mat. 3.6. <hi>ergo</hi> ſo is the ſecond. <hi>I anſw.</hi> This alſo is true in men of yeares, who are converted from Heatheniſme to the Chriſtian Religion; ſo it was when any were converted to the Jewiſh Religion, but what is this to Infants, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jewes, or Chriſtians. Againe, when multitudes came to <hi>John</hi> to be baptized of him, ſome few of them might confeſſe the ſinnes of all, as being the mouth of the people to God, as any Miniſter is in his Congregation, then this hinders not; but theirs and our Infants may be baptized.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, they Object, if none muſt be baptized but ſuch as beleeve, then Infants may not be baptized. But the firſt is true, Mark 16.16. Acts 8.36, 37. <hi>ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond. <hi>I Anſw.</hi> If none but ſuch as we know doe truely beleeve muſt be baptized, then we muſt baptize none at all, becauſe we know no mans heart, and Faith is that new name written which none knowes but he that receives it, Revel. 2.7. Againe, if none muſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed but true beleevers, and we cannot know them, we may ſoone miſtake, and ſet the token of the Covenant upon Reprobates, and refuſe to give it to the Elect. Againe, Chriſt ſaid, Thoſe little ones that he tooke in his Armes did beleeve in him, ſee Mat. 16.6. compared with Luke 9.26, and their hearts may as well be knowne to us as the hearts of men of yeares, for we know the hearts of none. Again, that faith that was required was but to beleeve that Chriſt was the Son of God, and that the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion was the true Religion; but Infants of Chriſtians have taken up no falſe Religion, then it need not be required that they ſhould beleeve the true, being brought up in none other. Againe, to baptize none but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:125273:4"/>thoſe that doe truly beleeve were the direct way to caſt out the token of the <hi>Covenant</hi> altogether, becauſe we cannot truly know them, then wee ought not to neglect this duty to baptize Infants.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, They ſay, if none ought to be baptized but ſuch as make profeſſion of juſtifying faith, then Infants ought not to be baptized; but Infants cannot make ſuch profeſſion. And ſaith Maſter <hi>Tombes,</hi> Neither <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> nor the Apoſtles would baptize any without ſome ſhewes of faith and repentance. And although he grants, that Infants may have a right to Heaven, yet they muſt not be baptized till that appeare. But I ſay, their hearts will never be knowne to us, then they had as good ſay they ſhall never be baptized, as to ſay, they ſhall not be baptized till they know their hearts. Againe, would not the Apoſtles baptize any unleſſe they profeſſe a lye, &amp; that in the preſence of Chriſt who knew their hearts, and then might they lawfully be baptized when they had profeſſed a lye in the preſence of Chriſt, for they baptized alwaies in his preſence before his death, <hi>John.</hi> 3.22.26.42. that they might be his Diſciples and not theirs. And would Chriſt have all thoſe to profeſſe that they had true juſtifying faith? when as he knew their hearts and would not truſt them, <hi>John.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 23, 24. What horrible blaſphemy is this? No, they were required but to beleeve that Chriſt was the Sonne of God, and his Religion was the true Religion, and then they had right to Baptiſme in the approbation of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles; and their parents profeſſion might be imputed to the child, becauſe they have power to bring them up in that Religion they profeſſe, as well as the Jewes had power to bring up their Infants in their Religion; neither had their Infants any other profeſſion but that of their parents; then chriſtian Infants may as well be baptized as Jewiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were circumciſed.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, They object againſt my ſecond ground, ſaying, The gift of the Holy Ghoſt there promiſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.39. is not the ſanctifying Gift, but the gift of Tongues, and miracles to caſt out Divels, and to cure all manner of diſeaſes, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.17. <hi>I anſw. John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was filled with the Holy Ghoſt from his mothers wombe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.15. to ſhew that as he was fit for Baptiſme from the wombe, ſo he ſhould judge of others: Neither could that be the gift of tongues, nor the gift of miracles as ſoon as he was born, but the gift of ſanctification which <hi>Jeremiah</hi> had before he was borne, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. Then if Infants may be ſo baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, wee may not deny them the outward forme of Baptiſme. But ſaith Maſter <hi>Tombes,</hi> That promiſe is to Jewes that were called of the ſending of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from theſe Texts, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.25.26.13.32.33. This we grant. But then he ſaith, Mention is made of a Promiſe, not as of it ſelfe, yeelding right to Baptiſme without repentance, but as a motive to thoſe that repent and are baptized. But to this we grant, that Baptiſme without repentance is of no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:125273:5"/>value; But when we heare the Baptiſme of the Holy Ghoſt is promiſed to chriſtian Infants, and they have power to bring them up in the chriſtian Religion, then I would know why ſuch may not be baptized, having no falſe Religion to repent of, and the promiſe of the inward Baptiſme; thus ſure their parents that have power to bring them up in the true Religion, have alſo power to ſet the marke of a chriſtian upon them, to be knowne from Turks and Infidels. But then he ſaith, That Promiſe was made to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh Infants, and therefore not to chriſtian Infants, but this is a meere ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill againſt the Text, and not worth anſwering.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, They object againſt my third ground, ſaying, That the holyneſſe which children have from their parents, is nothing elſe but this, thoſe parents have a ſanctified uſe of them, for unto the pure all things are pure, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15. I anſwer, If all things be pure unto them, then other mens children, yea Infidels children are pure unto them, yea the ſtones and Beaſts of the Field are at peace with them, <hi>Job.</hi> 5.23. yea they have a ſanctified uſe both of the evill of ſinne and the evill of puniſhment, for all things ſhall worke together for their good that love God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. but this benefit comes not by marrying of beleevers, but by our marriage with Chriſt; but this had beene to ſmall purpoſe for <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers have a ſanctified uſe of their children, when as he had not onely ſaid before, they have a ſanctified uſe of them, but of all things elſe; then the meaning is this, they have ſuch a holineſſe as the Jewes had, to diſtinguiſh them from other Nations, to be of the church of God, a holy Nation; ſo Infants of chriſtians are diſtinguiſhed from Turks and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, to be of the viſible church, as well as the Jewiſh Infants by this marke of diſtinction: now they are holy, therefore they ought to be baptized. But Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, That holineſſe ſpoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. is nothing elſe but this, they are legitimate, that is, they are not baſtards. To this I anſwer, That the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were Gentiles or Heathens before <hi>Paul</hi> preached amongſt them, and by his preaching ſome times he converted a wife to the chriſtian Religion, and could not convert the husband, and ſometimes the husband and not the wife, but if either of them was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from their dumbe Idols wherein they were led, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.2. to the chriſtian faith, now, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> your children are holy: It ſeemes when either of them was converted the great queſtion to the Apoſtle was this, Whether their children had a right to the Ordinance of Baptiſme, and ſo to all other priviledges of the chriſtian church? To this a ſecret anſwer is implyed, That they had a right to all the Ordinances and priviledges of the chriſtian church, for now, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> your children are holy, that is, they are diſtinguiſhed now from Heathens and Infidels children, ſo that now one of the parents is become a chriſtian, it cannot be ſaid now that they are Infidels children; but when both the parents were converted to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:125273:5"/>the chriſtian Religion, then the matter was out of queſtion, ſo that then they need not aske whether their children ſhould enjoy the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the chriſtian church; this being the true genuine meaning of the Text: Now let us ſee what truth is in Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> interpretation of it, ſaying, Now they are legittimate, now they are not baſtards; but can any rationall man think this, that if a mans wife was conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the chriſtian Religion, that then ſhee would come to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to aske them whether or not their children were baſtards; could any man living tell that better then ſhee her ſelfe; if ſhee were a whore then they were baſtards, but not elſe. Againe, them that were lawfully married before <hi>Paul</hi> came amongſt them, and had children, they were not baſtards by Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> owne confeſſion; but ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> of thoſe children, that they were uncleane then, but now ſaith he, they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe one of the Parents is become a chriſtian, now thoſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are not heathens but chriſtians; ſo then, if the ſame children which before were uncleane, and now are holy by the converſion of one of the Parents, it muſt needs be ſuch a holineſſe to diſtinguiſh them from Infidels, to be of the true chriſtian Church; then he that denies this truth, muſt needes draw this concluſion, that the ſame children which before <hi>Paul</hi> came there were baſtards, but now one of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents is converted to the chriſtian Religion, thoſe children that were baſtards and uncleane, are now holy and no baſtards. Againe, ſhall we be ſuch fools, as to think, becauſe the husband is a Chriſtian, that his chriſtianity will ſo ſanctifie his wife, that ſhee cannot have a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, or will her being a chriſtian ſo ſanctifie her husband that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have a baſtard; if this were true, then how comes it to paſſe that we have ſo many baſtards in <hi>Engl.</hi> when both the husband &amp; the wife pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelves to be chriſtians, and yet ſometimes both of them are ſo prophane as to have baſtards? then I ſay, that holineſſe ſpoken of by <hi>Paul</hi> is that mark of diſtinction to be knowne from Turks and Infidels to be of the viſible Church of Chriſt, and therefore have a true right to baptiſme, and ſo to all other Ordinances and priviledges of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, although infancy or ſickneſſe may hinder them from ſome of them, yet it cannot from baptiſme, being onely paſſive, the work is done upon them, and no action required of them, therefore they may and ought to be baptized.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, they object againſt my fifth ground, ſaying, that command of God ceaſed, which did command to ſet the token of the Covenant upon Jewiſh Infants, when Chriſt came and changed that token of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion into baptiſme: But I ſay, the command remaines, although the token be changed; as for inſtance: God commanded the children
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:125273:6"/>of Iſrael to keepe holy the ſeventh day, for it was the Sabbath of the Lord their God; but this command remaines, although by Chriſt the day was changed; and ſo for other commands to Iſrael, thou ſhalt have no other gods but me; thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any graven image, nor bow downe unto it, nor take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine; but although the Church of the Jewes be cut off, and the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church grafted in, we may not ſay theſe commands were repeald when the Church was changed, and ſo conclude that Chriſtians may have other gods, and bow downe to them, and worſhip them, and take the name of Iſraels God in vaine, becauſe the command was not made to us, but to them; nor keep no Sabbath, becauſe the command was made to them and not to us; nor ſet the token of the Covenant on our children, becauſe it was to them and not to us, becauſe our Church and Sabbath, and token of the Covenant was all changed; then unleſſe you be minded to caſt off God, the Sabbath, the Sacraments, the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, let your children be baptized.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, they object, ſaying, thoſe that have a right to one of the Sacraments, have a right to both, but Infants have no right to the Lords Supper, becauſe they cannot examine themſelves, nor remember the death of Chriſt, nor diſcerne his body in the Sacrament, then Infants may not be baptized. <hi>I anſw.</hi> Thoſe impediments that hinder them from receiving the Lords Supper, are no impediments to hinder them from Baptiſme, becauſe nothing is required in the baptized Infants; they are meerly paſſive, the work is done upon them, when as the Lords ſupper requires many actions, as to take, eat, doe this, in men of age and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Againe, I doubt not but Infants have a right to both Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and all other Ordinances, although by naturall infirmities they are for the preſent diſabled from ſome of them, as by ſickneſſe or infancy; yet this hinders not, nor diſables any from Baptiſme, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Infants ought to be baptized, although baptiſme is not of abſolute neceſſity where it cannot be had, yet this contempt of it is damnable, but in times of perſecution, or in a journey, it may be deferred, as Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el did in the Wilderneſſe forty yeers, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.5. but they might not doe ſo in <hi>Canaan,</hi> for if they doe, it may be their children when they come to age would deſpiſe that Ordinance, and then they are to be cut off from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they have broken the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. and how doe theſe men know but their children will deſpiſe the covenant when they come to age? Nay, I dare ſay, it is the onely way to make them deſpiſe it when they come to age; for it is ſaid, <hi>all the people that heard Chriſt, and the Publicans, juſtified God, being baptized with the baptiſme of</hi> John (that is) <hi>with water,</hi> Mat. 3.11. <hi>but the Phariſes and Lawyers rejected
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:125273:6"/>the Councell of God, being not baptized of</hi> John, Luke 7.29.30. And it were a juſt judgement of God upon ſuch Parents, that will not ſet that marke of diſtinction, to ſever their children from Turks by baptiſme, that they ſhould never be ſevered from corrupted nature to the ſtate of grace; then to avoid this, let them be baptized.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, they object, that if Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>learne of me,</hi> was not baptized till he was 30 yeers old, then Infants muſt not be baptized, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.23. But the firſt is true, <hi>ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond. <hi>I anſw.</hi> It is true that Chriſt bad us learne of him to be humble and meek, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. but he did not bid us learne of him to be 30 yeers old before that we be baptized, and if we learne that, we muſt neither be more nor leſſe but juſt of his age. Againe, he was both circumcized and baptized, but he did not bid us learne both. Againe, at thirty yeeres old he put an end to the Jewiſh Religion, and could not be baptized before; neither could he ſet up Chriſtian Religion, till he had put downe the Jewiſh Religion: But I would not have the Anabaptiſts to tarry till they be thirty yeers old be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they become Chriſtians, and ſay they learned to doe ſo of Chriſt. Againe, at the ſame time, others were baptized at ſeverall ages, ſome more, ſome leſſe then the age of Chriſt; then the matter lay in this, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were converted from falſe Religions to the true Religion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were not converted from the ſtate of corrupted nature to the ſtate of grace, they baptized them; we read of none that ever were denied to be baptized but the Phariſes and Sadduces who came to <hi>John</hi> to be baptized; but he refuſed to baptize them, becauſe they would not leave their ſects and ſciſmes, they would be Phariſes and Sadduces ſtill, therefore he cals them <hi>A generation of Vipers,</hi> Mat. 3.7. becauſe ſuch would eat out the bowels of the chriſtian Church; this might be an item to all the ſects and ſciſmes amongſt us, who are no better then Vipers both to Church and State; but when any was admitted to Baptiſme, if they did but beleeve that Chriſt was the Sonne of God, and his was the true Religion; I ſay, although they ſhould become Papiſts or prophane drunkards, or ſwearers, or adulterers, and ſhould be excommunicated for ſuch wickedneſſe, yet ſtill they having a right to the Ordinances, as a Free-man hath of a Corporation, although for the preſent he be in priſon, and cannot make uſe of it, till he hath compounded with his adverſarice, and this man given ſatisfaction to the Church; therefore his children ought to be baptized, unleſſe the Parents turn Turks, and ſo renounce Chriſt and chriſtian Religion, yet if but one of them ſhould doe this, their children are holy, and ought to be baptized, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all other failings whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, thee object, if none muſt be baptized, and ſo receive the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:125273:7"/>token of the Covenant but ſuch as have the Covenant, then Infants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not be baptized; but they ſay the firſt is true, becauſe they are uncapable to receive the covenant, therefore they ought not to be baptized, which is the token of the covenant. Here I might anſwer, that chriſtian Infants are as capable both to receive the covenant and the token of it, as the Jewiſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were; but it is not true to ſay they onely that have the covenant muſt have the ſignes and tokens of it, for the male children of the Jewes all had the token of the covenant, both the elect and reprobates without any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and women which were in the covenant of grace as well as men, yet the ſigne and token of it was ſet onely on men, though reprobates, rather then on women, though never ſo faithfull; for the token of the covenant is not given as a perſonall benefit to all that have it, but it is given for the good of Gods people, who ought to rejoyce and be thankfull for it where-ever they ſee it; God made a covenant with <hi>Adam,</hi> but the token of it was ſet on trees; and God made a covenant with <hi>Noah,</hi> but the token of it was ſet in the clouds; ſo God might have ſet the token of the covenant of grace in the clouds or on trees, or onely on wicked men if he had ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; then ſhall we quarrell with God, and ſay, we will have the token of the covenant ſet onely on ſuch as have the covenant, as if the rain-bow ſhould be ſet on all men ſince <hi>Noahs</hi> flood; no, let us do as faithfull women did in the Church of the Jewes, who could rejoyce and be thankfull for the token of the covenant of grace, although it was not ſet on them but on men onely, and many of them reprobates; you we doe not find that ever they murmured againſt God, becauſe they had not the token of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant upon them as well as men; then I conclude, notwithſtanding theſe objections, that chriſtian Infants ought to be baptized.</p>
               <p>But Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> hath ſome more places of Scripture to examine, the firſt is <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. from which we prove that God did eſtabliſh his everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Covenant to <hi>Abraham;</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> 21. he eſtabliſhed that everlaſting covenant alſo with <hi>Iſaac;</hi> and being eſtabliſhed thus to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> then it was alſo confirmed unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> for an everlaſting covenant, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105, 10. But this covenant was made with Chriſt from all eternity; ſo <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.23. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.2. now circumciſion was a token of that everlaſting covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 11. and not a token that they ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſo it ſutes with baptiſme, which is alſo a token of that everlaſting covenant, which God the Father made with God the Son from all eternity; but Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, that Covenant to which cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion had relation, being eſtabliſhed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he ſaith was a mixed covenant, and therfore not the ſame with ours. <hi>I anſw.</hi> All temporall promiſes both to <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſterity and alſo to us, are but the over-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe promiſes contained in that everſting covenant, for godlineſſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:125273:7"/>hath the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. ſeek the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. ſo then, we have as many promiſes of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things as the Jewes had; but then to encreaſe his doubting, he ſaith, <hi>Abraham's</hi> ſeed is many wayes to be taken. <hi>I anſw.</hi> The ſeed to whom the covenant was made was but one, and that was Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. and to all the elect when they are grafted into Chriſt by faith, as we enter into the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> covenant when we come to have his image of nature, ſo we come into the ſecond <hi>Adams</hi> covenant when we come to have his image of grace; now circumciſion was the token of this covenant to the Jewes, as baptiſme is to Chriſtians; but I ſhall ſpeak more fully of this, in anſwer to Captaine <hi>Hobſons</hi> firſt argument.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, to encreaſe his doubtings, that if baptiſm ſucceed circumciſion, then none but males ought to be baptized, becauſe none but males were circumciſed, and <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt did baptize before cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of right ceaſed, therefore it doth not ſucceed circumciſion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they both ſignifie the righteouſneſſe of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.6.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. and the ſame ſanctification of the heart, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. But ſaith he, they differ in ſome things; firſt, circumciſion did ſignifie, that Chriſt ſhould come of <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 17.21. but baptiſme doth ſignifie his death and reſurrection. <hi>I anſw.</hi> although they are both tokens of the ſame covenant, yet they may in ſome things differ in their ſignification, and yet agree well together, thus: circumciſion more lively ſignified mortification, and the death of ſinne in the crucifying and death of Chriſt, and of juſtifying the ſinner by the blood of Chriſt; and baptiſme more cleerly ſignifies the buriall of ſinne in the buriall of Chriſt, and riſing from the death of ſinne to the life of grace by the reſurrection of Chriſt, and waſhing away our ſinnes by the ſpirit of Chriſt, he being under water, and aroſe out of the water, and as water waſheth away the filth of our bodies, ſo the blood of Chriſt waſheth away our ſinnes; but to ſay circumciſion was a token, that Chriſt ſhould come of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> contradicts it himſelfe, ſaying; <hi>John</hi> baptized before circumciſion ſhould of right ceaſe, and yet Chriſt was borne thirty yeeres before, which hangs together like harpe and harrow; and <hi>Paul</hi> circumciſed <hi>Timothy</hi> after Chriſts aſſention, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. and after he had preached of his reſurrection many times; but this had been notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wicked, if circumciſion had ſignified that Chriſt was yet for to come of <hi>Iſaac:</hi> ſecondly, he ſaith circumciſion ſignified that the Iſraelites were ſeperated from all Nations; but I ſay no, for if any would turne to the Jewes Religion they ſhould be circumcized, let them be of what Nation they would; ſo then it was onely a note of diſtinction of their Religion from all other, and that they onely had the true viſible Church of God, and ſo baptiſme is one mark of the chriſtian Church, whereby it is known
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:125273:8"/>from Turks and Infidels: Thirdly, he faith circumciſion ſignified that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> Law was to be obſerved, from <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. But how can that be, when it was not given till four hundred yeers after: fourthly, he faith circumciſion did ſigne the promiſe of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to them, and baptiſme ſignes eternall life by Chriſt: But I ſay, they both ſignifie and ſigne the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of that everlaſting covenant made with Chriſt for the elect, yet not to all that have it, but to Gods people that are amongſt us; and for <hi>Canaan,</hi> I ſay it was but an overplus, of thoſe promiſes which we enjoy as well as the Jewes, when as ſpirituall and eternall mercies were the principall things intended in that everlaſting covenant; and whereas he ſaid, if baptiſme ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed circumciſion, then none but males muſt be baptized. I have anſwered, the command by Chriſt is now enlarged to all Nations, and to females; if this man be not faithleſſe, but faithfull, I ſuppoſe this may ſatisfie the doubt from this Scripture, why chriſtian infants may not be baptized.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, his examination of other Scriptures, to encreaſe his doubtings are theſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 32, 33.18.8. 1 Cor. 1.16. he ſaith, the words to the Jaylor were ſpoke to all in his houſe, and he rejoyced, beleeving God with all his houſhold; and <hi>Criſpus</hi> beleeved God with all his houſe, and was baptized; hence he concludes, that the name of the whole houſe is to be underſtood, that thoſe which beleeved in it onely were baptized: But I have anſwered already, that if but one of the Parents become a chriſtian, the children are holy, which cannot be denied by any Scripture or ſound reaſon: And againe, he hath ſaid nothing of <hi>Liddiahs</hi> houſhold; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, although the Jaylor had ſervants which beleeved by hearing and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtles carriage in the priſon, yet <hi>Liddia</hi> was a ſtranger, going to heare <hi>Paul</hi> preach, was converted, and he came and baptized her whole houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold immediately, and it may be never ſaw them before; neither was it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall, whether children was of age or not, it may ſuffice, that they bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed whole houſholds, of which Infants was a part; and I ſay againe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they were uncleane before, if but one of the Parents beleeved, and was baptized, yet now they are holy, and if both Parents profeſſe themſelves chriſtians, which is our caſe in <hi>England,</hi> the matter is out of doubt, there Infants ought to be baptized. Againe, when God gave the token of the covenant to <hi>Abraham,</hi> he commanded that the token ſhould be ſet on all the males in his houſe, and he accordingly obeyed, and did ſo, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12.27. and ſaith the Lord, <hi>I know that Abraham will teach his children and his houſhold after him to keep the way of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 18.10. and ſaith <hi>Joſhua, as for me and my houſhold we will ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 24.15. Now I have ſaid and proved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that Chriſt came not to take away the token of the covenant, but to change it, and to enlarge it, but the covenant and the command are both the ſame, and remaine ſtill; ſee my anſwer to the ninth Objection; then it is cleare, that if houſholds were circumciſed and baptized, then our Infants may and ought to be baptized.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:125273:8"/>
               <p> I ſhall anſwer two Queſtions: Suppoſe where heathens and chriſtians live in a land together, yet at ſome diſtance, and the heathen ſhould take away a chriſtians Infant before it be baptized, and reſolve to keep it by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence from them, only they will give the chriſtian leave to come with a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and baptize it, but they will not part with the child; now may this man goe and baptize it, and engage himſelfe to bring it up in the chriſtian Religion: <hi>I anſw.</hi> No; it were ſin and folly to promiſe that which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not performe, the child being kept out of his hands by Infidels; yea, it were as bad and ſinfull to doe as thoſe did under the Prelats government, who did engage themſelves, that the child ſhould forſake the devill and all his works, and all the luſts of the fleſh, and beleeve the Articles of the chriſtian faith, and keepe all Gods Commandements, therefore it ought not to be done. The ſecond Queſtion is this; ſuppoſe a child of heatheniſh Infidels ſhould by ſome providence of God, lawfully come under the government of chriſtians, ought the child to be baptized? <hi>I anſw.</hi> Yes, becauſe they have power to bring it up in the chriſtian Religion, therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to circumciſe al the males in his houſe, ſome of them being children of Infidels, becauſe the Lord knew that <hi>Abraham</hi> would command his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold to doe that which is right in the ſight of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and chriſtians have the ſame power to bring up thoſe under their government in the chriſtian Religion; and this alſo may anſwer Maſter <hi>Tombes,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Infants baptiſme may be a meanes to baptize them of uncertaine progeny:</hi> But I ſay, if chriſtians have power to bring them up in the chriſtian Religion, and they can bring them up in no other, becauſe the whole Kingdome hath embraced it; neither need they now to have any ſureties to engage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to bring them up in it, ſeeing the whole Kingdome hath embraced it and doe profeſſe it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, Baptiſme is doubtfull, becauſe it cannot be proved that it was in uſe in the next age after the Apoſtles. Fifthly, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, Infants baptiſme is doubtfull, becauſe in the ſucceeding age afterwards, it was held to be a written tradition. <hi>I anſw.</hi> If it be proved that it was in the Apoſtles times, and that by the command of Chriſt, then the Apoſtacy of the times cannot make it unlawfull; but the firſt is proved ſufficiently, yet more ſhall be ſaid to it in anſwer to Captaine <hi>Hobſon's</hi> third argument; then this doth not juſtly hinder chriſtians Infants from bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, Infants baptiſme hath occaſioned many hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inventions to underprop it: Firſt, ſureties in baptiſme; ſecondly, epiſcopall confirmation; thirdly, the reformed union by examination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Communion; fourthly, the Church-covenant as it is in New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>I anſw.</hi> theſe are all meere ſcandals caſt upon the Presbyteriall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which doth utterly ſuppreſſe them all.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:125273:9"/>
               <p> Seventhly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, Infants baptiſme hath occaſioned or hath been as the birth to foſter many errours; firſt, that baptiſme conferres grace by the work done; ſecondly, baptiſme is regeneration; thirdly, that Infants dying, are ſaved by the faith of the Parents; fourthly, that ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate may fall from grace. <hi>I anſw.</hi> The abuſe of Infants baptiſme doth not nullifie it, neither can it be truly ſaid to be the ground of theſe errours, for we hold that it may be done upon reprobates as well as circumciſion was, neither is it a perſonall benefit to thoſe that have it, but it is onely given as a benefit to the godly, who live amongſt them; and ſo the baptiſme of reprobates may benefit the godly, although it doth not benefit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that have it.</p>
               <p>Eightly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, baptiſme of Infants cauſeth many faults in diſcipline, and in divine worſhip, and in converſation, ſuch as theſe; firſt private baptiſme; ſecondly, baptiſme of Infants; thirdly, baptiſme by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; fourthly, baptiſme of uncertaine Progeny; fifthly, baptiſme in the name of the Lord, who know not the Lord nor have ever conſented, and perhaps will never conſent to the confeſſion of the name of the Lord: ſixthly, it hath brought in the admiſſion of ignorant and prophane to the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Lords ſupper: ſeventhly, it perverts the order of diſcipline to to baptize and then to catechize: eighthly, it turnes the Sacrament into a ceremony or prophane feaſting: ninthly, it makes men forget that ever they were baptized: tenthly, it takes away or diminiſheth zeale and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry to know the Goſpell. <hi>I anſw.</hi> Moſt of theſe are ſcandals without any proofe, as the five laſt, and there is but one of the other five altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, and that is baptiſme by women; and yet this is held by ſome Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts to be lawfull, which is not lawfull, but abominable, and he makes a perhaps to the fifth, where there is no cauſe, for the Parents have power to bring them up to profeſſe the chriſtian Religion, which is as much as the Apoſtles required before they did admit them to baptiſme; then theſe ten faults are not ſufficient to hinder chriſtian Infants from baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, that Infants baptiſme is an occaſion of many unneceſſary diſputes, foſtering contention, which can never be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by any certaine rule, ſuch as theſe; firſt, baptizing Infants of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated perſons: ſecondly, baptizing Infants of apoſtates: thirdly, baptizing Infants of Parents that are not members of a gathered Church: fourthly, baptizing Infants of thoſe whoſe Anceſtors were beleevers, and the next Parents remaining ſtill in unbeliefe. <hi>I anſw.</hi> the firſt and laſt of theſe the Church of <hi>England</hi> makes no doubt of, nor of the ſecond, unleſſe they turne Turks, and ſo renounce the chriſtian Religion; and the third is a meer cavill of Independents, for he that is baptized into the chriſtian faith and Religion, is a member of the chriſtian Church, where-ever he is; then notwithſtanding this argument, chriſtian Infants ought to be baptized.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:125273:9"/>
               <p> Tenthly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, That Baptiſme of Infants was oppoſed in the midſt of the darkneſſe of Popery, by the ſame men that oppoſed invocation of Saints, and prayer for the dead, and adoration of the Croſſe. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> In the midſt of that darkneſſe ſome light might be hid from thoſe that ſought to bring in the light of the Goſpell; but we need not to fetch proofe from thoſe darke times, for <hi>Luther</hi> denyed ſome part of Scripture to be the Word of God, and he held conſubſtantiation, ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Chriſts body, and yet he withſtood Popery more powerfully then any of thoſe before him. Then this cannot hinder Infants Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, the aſſertors of Infants Baptiſme do not agree amongſt themſelves, upon what foundation they may build it. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> Though ſeverall men bring ſeverall arguments for it, this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it. Againe, they all agree in the command of Chriſt, and the promiſe of ſanctifying grace, and the bleſſing and teſtimony of Chriſt on them, and of that holineſſe of diſtinction from Turks and Infidels; and if ſome bring more arguments to confirme it, ſhall this make it void? and what truth is that which was never oppoſed by ſome? then this cannot hinder Infants Baptiſme,</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> ſaith, Infants Baptiſme ſeemes to take away one of the prime ends of Baptiſme, which was to ſhew and confeſſe himſelfe to be a Diſciple; but this I have already anſwered ſeverall times, ſo then, notwithſtanding all theſe doubtfull arguments, here is nothing that may juſtly hinder Chriſtian Infants from Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>All theſe doubts are briefly mentioned by Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Booke, Intituled, <hi>An exercitation of Infants Baptiſme,</hi> before his Anſwer to Maſter <hi>Marſhall,</hi> therefore I forbeare to ſet downe the ſeverall pages to finde them.</p>
               <p>Here I ſhall ſpeake ſomething touching re-baptizing, or often baptizing, becauſe Maſter <hi>Tombes</hi> in his great Booke ſeemes to favour it, ſaying, If we had as cleare Scripture for Infants Baptiſme as we have for re-bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, our controverſie would ſoone be ended; and by other ſuch like paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in his Booke. It appeares that he favours re-baptizing or often Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; then ſuppoſe any that is baptized in the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould queſtion the lawfulneſſe of their Baptiſme, ſaying, I was not rightly bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed becauſe I was an Infant, and knew not what was done, but this I have already anſwered; then ſuppoſe another ſay, I was ſprinkled, which is to rinſe and not to baptize, therefore I was not rightly baptized; this I ſhall anſwer in the ſecond point. Then ſuppoſe another ſay, I was baptized ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a drunken Prieſt, that cannot preach and baptize as he ought, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. or elſe by a Popiſh Prieſt, who had his Ordination from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Biſhops, therefore I was not rightly baptized, and may be re-baptized. But here I would know how our Anabaptiſts Preachers can prove their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:125273:10"/>owne calling lawfull; If they ſay that they are teaching Diſciples, then where is their Ordination? it was either from men of other callings, who have nothing to do in it, or elſe they have none at all; and how was their firſt teacher made? it was ſure the Divell that firſt moved him from his place and calling to become their Teacher. And if they ſay, his Calling was extraordinary, like that of the Apoſtles, then we would ſee their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts, and till then we cannot believe their Calling to be lawfull, and ſo themſelves ought not to preach nor baptize; thus while they judge our Miniſters they condemne themſelves; And for our Biſhops and Miniſters I anſwer and ſay, That they were ordained by men of their owne calling, to preach and to adminiſter the Sacraments, and thus it hath beene ſucceſſively from the Apoſtles, and although the Biſhops had power and authority given them by men to rule over their Brethren, which they ought not, yet that did not make void that which they had from God, for then that or any other ſinne, would make that or any other cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling void, ſo that a man muſt either live without ſinne or be caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>red of his calling; ſo then our Miniſters ſtanding is lawfull, and their Baptiſme warrantable. I need not ſpeake of the Service Booke, the Croſſe, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſe, which were the onely things that troubled them, but they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, and yet they ſtand out as much as ever, which ſhewes they have proud and froward hearts, rather then any juſt cauſe given to them, why they ſhould forſake our Churches. But ſuppoſe there were ſome exception againſt our Miniſters entrance or execution of their office, yet that will not make their Baptiſme void; the Lord was wrath with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and would have killed him becauſe his child was not circumciſed, but when that was done his wrath ceaſed, although it was done by his wife, a woman, and an outlandiſh woman, and in her rage againſt God for commanding ſuch a ſervice, and againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> for being willing to yeeld unto ſuch a ſervice, ſee <hi>Exud.</hi> 4.24, 25, 26. Then may not our Miniſters baptize as lawfully and acceptably as this woman might circumciſe. Now I grant, if our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould baptize in their own name, then their Baptiſme would be void, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.15. but they uſe the right forme which Chriſt gave the Apoſtles, in the name of the Trinity, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. and they uſe the right matter, which is water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.22. and on the right Subject, Chriſtians Infants, as hath been proved, and to the right end, which is, no diſtinguiſh them from Heathens and Infidels, and to engage them to obey the Covenant, of which Baptiſme is a figne or token; and all this is done by Miniſters law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called, therefore they ought not to be re-baptized. Againe, Baptiſme is a Sacrament of the new birth; and although we may come often to the other Sacrament, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.25. yet we can be borne but once; therefore we muſt take this Sacrament but once, which is the ſigne of it. Againe, there is but one Lord, one Faith, and one Baptiſme, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. therefore the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:125273:10"/>Sacrament of Baptiſme is to be adminiſtred but once. Their Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are now to be anſwered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they object, That if Chriſt ſaid he had another Baptiſme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that he had of <hi>John, Matth.</hi> 3.17. Then we may be againe baptized, but he ſaith, I have a Bapriſme to be baptized with, and how am I ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned till it be accompliſhed, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.50. then they may be againe baptized. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> That Baptiſme of Chriſt was his ſufferings, <hi>for,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to the Sonnes of Zebedy can yee drinke of the Cup that I drinke of, and be baptized with the Baptiſme that I am baptized with,</hi> and they ſaid, <hi>we are able;</hi> Then he ſaid, <hi>you ſhall indeed drinke of the Cup that I drinke of, and be baptized with the Baptiſme that I am baprized with, Mark.</hi> 10.38, 39. Therefore, ſaith <hi>Paul, We are baptized into his death, and buryed with him by Baptiſme, Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4. So then Chriſt was but once baptized with water, no more muſt we; but then as Chriſt was killed and crucified afterwards, ſo muſt we kill and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie our finnes daily afterwards; Then here is no warrant to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptized.</p>
               <p>Secondly, They object, That if thoſe that looke for a reſurrection muſt be baptized at their death, then there is more Baptiſmes then one; but <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, if the dead riſe not, why are they baptized for the dead, what ſhall they doe that are baptized for the dead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. therefore they may be againe baptized. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> Baptizing ſignifies waſhing, and it was the cuſtome to waſh the dead Corps, for when <hi>Doreas</hi> was dead they waſhed her body, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.37. but they that will be ſo baptized muſt tarry till they be dead, neither ſhall it be done by the Miniſter, but by them that ſhall winde them up and put them into the Coffin to be butied; but here is no Warrant to be re-baptized, from this Text, till after they be dead.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they object, That if ſome were twice baptized, then ſo may we, but ſome were firſt baptized by <hi>John,</hi> and afterwards by <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 5. then we may be againe baptized. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> ſome doe expound thoſe words to be thus underſtood; ſaying, They were firſt baptized by ſome falſe Diſciples of <hi>John</hi> into his name, and ſo it was void, and therefore they-were baptized againe in the name of Chriſt, but this cannot be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for then <hi>Paul</hi> would have inquired after thoſe Hereticks, for <hi>Paul</hi> was newly come from <hi>Corinth, v.</hi> 1. where he had cleared himſelfe from the ſame thing, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.13, 15. then ſure he would not ſo put it up at <hi>Epheſus.</hi> 2. Some expound thoſe words thus, ſaying, They were when <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Epheſus</hi> onely taught the Doctrine of <hi>John,</hi> but not baptized of him, and ſo were baptized by <hi>Paul;</hi> but this is not the meaning neither, for they were believers and they were Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. therefore they were baptized of <hi>John,</hi> and yet they had not learned his Doctrine, for they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew Jeſus Chriſt nor the Holy Ghoſt till <hi>Paul</hi> had told them, <hi>v.</hi> 3.4. Thirdly, The Anabaptiſts expound it thus; ſaying, They were baptized
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:125273:11"/>with water firſt by <hi>John,</hi> and then againe with water by <hi>Paul;</hi> but this is not the meaning neither, for their ſecond Baptiſme is not done with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; but while <hi>Paul</hi> was expounding to them who it was that <hi>John</hi> ſaid ſhould come after him, and baptize them with the Holy Ghoſt, that is, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>v.</hi> 4. Now when they heard this they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>v.</hi> 5. that is, while <hi>Paul</hi> was expounding, their ſouls was converted and baptized with the Holy Ghoſt; neither is here any word that <hi>Paul</hi> baptized them, onely he made knowne Chriſt to them, and when the worke was done they were baptized, as it was while <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake the Holy Ghoſt fell on them which heard the Word, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44. So then here is the full meaning of theſe words, they were baptized with water by <hi>Iohn,</hi> for they were Diſciples and believers, that is, they believed that the Chriſtian Religion was the true Religion, ſo that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from heatheniſme to chriſtianity, but they were not converted from the ſtate of corruption to the ſtate of grace, though <hi>Iohn</hi> had ſaid, He that comes after me ſhall baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt, but him they knew not, till <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, that is Jeſus Chriſt; by that word when they heard that they were converted and their ſouls waſhed or baptized with the Holy Ohoſt. But it may be they will object, ſaying, The Holy Ghoſt was given to them afterwards, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> That was the gift of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, to cure all diſeaſes, to caſt out Divels, and to ſpeake with divers Tongues, yet this alſo is called Baptiſme, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>You ſhall be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with the Holy Ghoſt not many daies hence, Act.</hi> 1.5. that is, the gift of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, but they had the ſanctifying gift before, for it was the ſanctifying gift that <hi>Iohn</hi> had from the wombe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.15 this is that promiſe made to us and our children, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38. ſo then ſome times the outward forme is called Baptiſme, and ſometimes ſanctification is called Baptiſme, and ſome times the gift of miracles is called Baptiſme, as <hi>Act.</hi> 1.5. and all theſe three are together in that 19. of the Act; for firſt they were baptized by water of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and then baptized by the Holy Ghoſt by <hi>Pauls</hi> teaching, and then they received the gift of miracles by <hi>Pauls</hi> laying on of his hands, and all this is but one Baptiſme, onely the outward forme is diſtinguiſhed from the inward and reall worke of the Holy Ghoſt. Then this Text will not warrant their re-baptizing the ſecond time with water.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, they object, That if <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of Baptiſmes in the Plural Number, then there is more Baptiſmes then one; but <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmes in the plural number, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.2. therefore there is more then one. <hi>I anſwer;</hi> It is like <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the outward and inward Baptiſme, and the gift of miracles, and cals them altogether Baptiſmes in the plural number; or it may be he puts the ſufferings of Chriſtians, and waſhing their corps after death, which are called Baptiſmes, becauſe the very next thing <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of is the reſurection; howſoever if <hi>Paul</hi> here ſpeaks
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:125273:11"/>of divers kinds of baptiſmes which it is moſt likely he doth, then this Text will not warrant a ſecond baptiſme with water, but <hi>Paul</hi> here ſpeakes of the Doctrine of Baptiſme and not of the forme, therefore it makes nothing for the outward forme to re-baptize them againe with water.</p>
               <p>Now as I was deſired I ſhall give a brief Anſwer to Captaine <hi>Hobſons</hi> five Arguments; Firſt ſaies he, the Baptiſme of Infants doth directly deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, becauſe it keepes on foot that which was before Chriſt, and ended by Chriſt as come in the fleſh; That is ſaith he, the Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> which ran in the fleſh, and was intailed to Generation, Gen. 17.7, 12. to this Covenant ſaith he, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion had reference, now thoſe naturall branches are cut off Rom. 11.20, 21. and now there are no Seed or Sonnes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but beleevers, Gal. 3.9.14.22.28.29. now the Promiſe is not a carnall, but a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, John 3.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I anſw.</hi> To ſay the Covenant which Circumciſion had reverence to was a Carnall Covenant, ſhewes but a carnall underſtanding of it, for it is called an everlaſting Covenant many times in that Chapter, Gen. 17. neither was this Covenant of Grace made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant with thee, and thy ſeed, every man childe ſhall be circumciſed, and this ſhall be a token of the Covenant, and this token ſhall be in your fleſh for that everlaſting Covenant, and my Covenant ſhall be eſtabliſhed with Iſaac.</hi> Then the Covenant was no more made with <hi>Abraham</hi> then it was with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but eſtabliſhed to both by that token of Circumciſion, ſo then that circumciſion was not a token of a carnall covenant, but a token of that eternall Covenant made between God the Father, and Chriſt his Sonne in our nature from all eternity: For, ſaith Chriſt, I was ſet up from everlaſting before the world was, Pro. 8.23. he was fore-ordained before the foundation of the world, 1 Pet. 1.20. God made promiſes to Chriſt before the world began, Titus 1.2. ſo then this eternall Covenant was not manifeſted by a token of it from the beginning of the world till <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> had it, becauſe till then no whole Nation was called into the viſible Church; but if <hi>Abraham</hi> and his poſterity had onely a token that they ſhould enjoy the Land of Canaan it had been but <hi>Eſaus</hi> bleſſing. Againe, to ſay that eternall Covenant was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> is to make him our Redeemer, for then he muſt performe the conditions of it for all the Elect, but (poore man) he had failings as well as other men, and not able to ſatisfie for his owne ſinnes, much leſſe for the ſinnes of all the Elect; ſo then that covenant was made with his ſeed, and ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> that ſeed was Chriſt, Gal. 3.16. Againe marke the concluſion of Maſter <hi>Hobſon,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Abraham</hi> received a token but of a carnall covenant, but if that were true, <hi>Abraham</hi> is damned; and then by and by he ſaith, the Seed and Sons of <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt be beleevers, Gal. 3.7.9.14.22.28.29. then ſure he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:125273:12"/>received the token of that everlaſting Covenant. But how are we Gentiles the Seed and Sons of <hi>Abraham? I anſwer.</hi> By receiving the ſigne and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that everlaſting covenant as a ſeale to our faith, as he did, Rom. 4.11. and we are his children by receiving the ſame faith in Chriſt as he had, but we are not <hi>Abrahams</hi> children as Chriſt is our everlaſting Father, who ſtood as a generall Perſon repreſenting all the Elect, and receiving a covenant for them, and able to fulfill the conditions of it, and to ſatisfie Gods Juſtice for the breach of <hi>Adams</hi> covenant, and able to worke faith in us to enter into his covenant: But when <hi>Abraham</hi> is named, we muſt underſtand him as an Embaſſadour, repreſenting Chriſt the King of his Church, with whom alone the new covenant was made, as the firſt was made with <hi>Adam,</hi> and all we come under it when we take upon us his naturall Image; ſo the ſecond covenant was made with Chriſt, and the Elect come under it when they receive his ſpirituall Image: ſo then the tokens of the covenant were before Chriſt came in the Fleſh, and Chriſt did not come to take away the token of the covenant, but to change them from Circumciſion to Baptiſme, and to enlarge them to all Nations, and to Females as well as Males, Acts 8.12. then the keeping on foot this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the covenant which Chriſt inſtituted after his comming in the fleſh doth not deny his comming in the fleſh, neither is this to hold circumciſion which was the token before his comming in the fleſh, then this Argument falls to nothing, whereby he would prove Infants Baptiſme to deny the comming of Chriſt in the fleſh. But then he ſaith, the Phariſees and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces pleading that they were <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, and would be Baptized, and yet <hi>John</hi> would not till they repent and beleeve, Mat. 3.7.8.9. <hi>I anſwer.</hi> If they had repented of their Sects and Schiſmes he would have Baptized them, for no ignorant Perſon was refuſed by him, although they had not heard whether there was any Holy Ghoſt, yet <hi>John</hi> baptized them unto repentance and bid them beleeve, and ſuch were made Diſciples, Acts 19.12, 34. but <hi>John</hi> knew that ſuch Sectaries would be but as Vipers to the true Religion, therefore he would not baptize them unleſſe they would leave their Hereſie and Schiſme. Then it was not becauſe they were of the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> that he refuſed it, but becauſe they would not leave their Hereſies and Schiſmes, this cannot keepe Infants from Baptiſme which have no Sects nor Schiſmes to repent of. But he hath another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove that the baptizing of Infants directly denies the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt in the fleſh, and that is this, He ſaith it takes from Chriſt his Propheticall and Kingly Offices, which the Holy Ghoſt gave him, as come in the Fleſh. <hi>I anſw.</hi> Chriſt had thoſe Offices before he came in the fleſh, he was King, and Prieſt to the Church of the Jewes, although not ſo manifeſt as to the chriſtian Church, but how the baptizing of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants ſhould rob Chriſt of thoſe Offices is a Paradox to all wiſe men. But
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:125273:12"/>he ſaith, becauſe it makes the Old Teſtament to expound the New, but what of this, Chriſt eates with ſinners, and ſome were offended at it, and he ſends them to the Old Teſtament, ſaying, <hi>Learne what that meaneth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> will have mercy and not ſacrifice,</hi> Mat. 9.13. but did Chriſt by this loſe his Propheticall Office, by ſending them to the Old Teſtament to expound his doings in the New? there is no truth in this Argument, nor in the thing that he would prove by it. But then he ſaith, baptizing of Infants robs Chriſt of his Kingly Office in giving Lawes, and making it a duty to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize infants. <hi>I anſw.</hi> They have a command from Chriſt to teach and baptize all Nations, but how is a Nation taught but when thoſe of yeares receive the chriſtian Religion, and make profeſſion of it by a poſitive Law of that Land, or elſe it were unpoſſible that any Nation ſhould be either taught or baptized, and ſo the Commiſſion of Chriſt would be to no purpoſe, and if children were excluded, how ſhall the Nations come in, as is promiſed? Iſa 22. Micah 4.2. but the truth is, if the Parents be of the Chriſtian Religion it is potentially in the childe, and the Parents have power to bring them up in that Religion, and therefore ought to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize them in it, but I ſhall ſpeake more of this in anſwer to his third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but this may ſuffice to prove that we have a command to baptize infants. Then we doe not intrench upon the Kingly Office of Chriſt, and there is neither ſence nor reaſon to ſay, if we did intrench upon his Kingly Office, that this were to deny his comming in the fleſh, when as his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office was before as well as ſince his comming in the fleſh, then all this hinders not infants Baptiſme; ſo much in anſwer to his firſt Argument, I ſhall be briefer in the reſt.</p>
               <p>His ſecond Argument is this, Infants Baptiſme hath no part of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in it, therefore it ought not to be done, his Propoſition is proved thus; Whatſoever is conſidered as a part of Righteouſneſſe was ſeene in the Perſon or Practice of Chriſt, but infants Baptiſme was neither ſeene in his Perſon nor Practice, for he was not baptized in his infancy, neither did he baptize any infants, and yet he ſaith it becomes us to fulfill all righteouſneſſe, Mat. 3.15. therefore infants may not be baptiſed. <hi>I anſwer;</hi> Chriſt came to fulfill the Morall Law, and ſo to free his people from that bond of perfect obedience to it, and he ſuffered the penalty due to our ſinnes to free us from the curſe of it; thus by his Active and Paſſive obedience he fulfilled all righteouſneſſe, this he did in his owne Perſon alone, and there was none with him, Iſa 63.3. Pſal. 47.8. but here in his anſwer to <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> he doth not ſay, it becommeth me, but <hi>it becommeth us to fulfill all righteouſneſſe,</hi> Mat. 3.15. Nay the action was <hi>Iohns,</hi> and not his, for Jeſus came to him to be baptized, verſe 13. ſo then I conceive the meaning to be this, <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſent or commanded to baptize with Water, ſee John 1.33. and he that beleeved that Jeſus was the Sonne of God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:125273:13"/>was to be baptized, Acts 8.37. but Jeſus, as a man, beleeved this, and therefore in obedience to that command was to doe it, and Jeſus to ſuffer it, thus ſaith Jeſus, <hi>It becommeth us to fulfill all righteouſneſſe,</hi> but it did not become <hi>Iohn</hi> to baptize before he was ſent to doe it, nor Jeſus to ſuffer before the command was given to <hi>Iohn</hi> to baptize, John 3.33. Then he could not be baptized in his infancy, becauſe the command was not then given. Againe, if he had been baptized in his infancy, then it might be queſtioned whether men of yeares might be baptized; neither would the Heathen have ſuffered their children, unleſſe themſelves had been admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to baptiſme; and Chriſt was baptized in the middle of his age, that neither infants; nor old age might be excluded from baptiſme. Againe, Jeſus came to be Baptized as ſoone as there was one appointed and ſent to doe it, then if we have lawfull Miniſters found to baptize our Infants, we ought to ſuffer them to doe it, becauſe it becommeth us to fulfill the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous command of Chriſt; but if it be with us as it was with Chriſt, that we have no lawfull Miniſter to doe it till we be of his age, then we may lawfully ſtay as long as he die before we baptize our infants. But then the Captaine ſaith, If God would have had Jeſus baptized ſooner, he would have ſent one ſooner to doe it. To this I may ſay, If God would not have our infants baptized, then he would not ſend Miniſters to them ſo ſoone to doe it. And whereas the Captaine faith, It is no part of righteouſneſſe becauſe Chriſt baptized no infants. To this I may anſwer, Chriſt baptized none at all with water, John 4.2. then if this Argument were good, it is no part of righteouſneſſe to baptize infants either young or old; but I ſhall prove it to be a part of righteouſneſſe to baptize infants in anſwer to his next Argument, but for the preſent you ſee his proves removed by which he would prove infants baptiſme to have no part of righteouſneſſe in it, and therefore his Propoſition muſt needs fall; and notwithſtanding this Argument chriſtian infants ought to be baptized.</p>
               <p>His third Argument is this, The baptiſme of infants is not the baptiſme of Chriſt, becauſe it doth not anſwer his commiſſion, Mat. 28.19, 20. which is, Goe teach, diſcipling and baptizing, hence he concludes, that they muſt be taught, and diſciplined, and beleevers before they can be baptized, Marke 16.16. and this no infant can be, and ſo cannot anſwer the commiſſion, therefore muſt not be baptized. <hi>I anſw.</hi> That infants baptiſme is according to the commiſſion of Chriſt, for according to his Expoſition whole Nations muſt be taught, and diſciplined, and made beleevers, elſe they were ſent to doe that which is impoſſible. But how can a whole Nation be taught, diſciplined, and made beleevers <hi>I anſw.</hi> There is a two-ſold converſion, and two Sacraments anſwerable to this two-fold converſion; the firſt converſion is a turning from falſe religion to the true religion, and the other is a converſion from corrupted nature
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:125273:13"/>to the ſtate of grace? now he that hath the firſt of theſe to beleeve Chriſt to be the Son of God, and that the Chriſtian Religion is the true Religion, this man may be diſcipled being thus taught, and ſo may receive the firſt Sacrament; yea thus a whole Kingdom may be taught and may beleeve the true Religion, and ſo diſcipled, and receive the Sacrament of Baptiſme; yea when the Governours of a Kingdom ſhall be taught and beleeve the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion to be the true Religion, and ſhall ſettle it amongſt them by a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Law of the Land, and all parents and people of yeers in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom conſent unto it, then all that Kingdom is taught and muſt all be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized; for, what the parents have done, the children have potentially done, becauſe it is in the power of thoſe parents to bring them up in that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and not ſuffer their infants to be of any other; and having this power, they may alſo ſet the token or mark of diſtinction upon them, to baptize them that they may be known from <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens.</hi> Now if parents had not this power, then no Kingdom could ever receive the Goſpel and be a holy Nation as the <hi>Jew</hi>'s was; and ſo their priviledge would exceed the priviledge of all Chriſtian Kingdoms; for there will be children to the end of the world; for till then, they will marry and be given in marriage till the laſt day. Then, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> received their Religion for themſelves and their children, ſo muſt Chriſtians, and ſet the token of the Covenant upon them as they did. But then, for the other converſion which makes them fit for the other Sacrament, the Lords Supper, it is not in the power of the parents; although they can bring them up in the Chriſtian Religion, yet they cannot convert them from the ſtate of corruption to the ſtate of grace; and although they be able to diſcern when they conform to the true Religion, yet they cannot ſee into their ſouls whether there be true Faith in them; that new name written none knows but he that hath it: then, although it be ſaid, <hi>Teach and baptize all Nations:</hi> yet it is not ſaid, <hi>Teach and give the Lords Supper to all Nations;</hi> for it is not in the power of man to teach effectually the heart of another, nor to know when they are ſo taught; none but himſelf knows whether he diſcern the Lords Body, or whether he ſeed by Faith or remember the Death of Chriſt, or whether he have truely examined himſelf; therefore the worthineſſe or unworthineſſe lies upon himſelf, and the charge alſo. Let every man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat. Neither muſt any baptized Chriſtian be kept from the Lords Supper, unleſſe he by the leaven of errour ſeek to undermine the truth of Chriſtian Religion, or by prophaneſſe trample the Chriſtian profeſſion underfoot, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12, 13. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.5, 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.9, 10. and then it muſt be done in a legall way, not by the Miniſter alone nor by the Congregation alone, but by the Elderſhip, the offence being ſcandalous. So then, the firſt converſion being in the power of the parents, and potentially in the children already, they may and ought to be baptized.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:125273:14"/>But then he ſaith, <hi>The Baptiſm of infants cannot be a Baptiſm of Faith and Repentance, and therefore it is not the Baptiſm of Christ.</hi> But in regard he hath no proof for it, I refer him to my anſwer to the ſecond and third Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conclude that Baptiſm of infants is not excluded from the Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt; and it is a Baptiſm unto Faith and Repentance, and therefore they ought to be baptized.</p>
               <p>His fourth Argument. He ſaith, <hi>Baptiſm of infants doth cauſe inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences in the Church; firſt, becauſe we make them Members of the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be called of God, which is contrary to theſe Scriptures,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. <hi>and</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. I anſwer, Though the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, and called to be Saints, yet all in the Church were not ſuch; for there was hereſies and prophaneſſe: the inceſtuous perſon was not caſt out; and the Lords Supper was prophaned; and more carnall men then ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall; and many diviſions, ſome of <hi>Paul</hi> and ſome of <hi>Apollo.</hi> Then, Were theſe all Saints? No. He writes in the judgement of charity, and directs his Epiſtle chiefly to ſuch as were Saints indeed; ſo then in the judgement of charity, we ſhould think the beſt of thoſe in the Church that uſe the means to attain ſalvation; and ſo you may judge of infants who are brought up in the true Religion: And although Heathens muſt have a call to Chriſtianity, yet when Chriſtians are called, their children need not to tarry for ſuch a call, becauſe they have no falſe Religion to be called from. Neither was it any inconvenience to the <hi>Jews</hi> that their infants had the token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant upon them before their calling; but rather a grace and glory to their Church, and a benefit to thoſe infants to engage them to obedience of that Covenant when they came to age, of which they had received a token. So all the people and the Publicans juſtified Chriſt when they heard him being baptized of <hi>John;</hi> when as the Phariſees and Lawyers rejected the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God againſt themſelves, being not baptized of him, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29, 30. Then as we would have them juſtifie Chriſt and not to reject his Counſell, let them be baptized. But he ſaith, <hi>Another inconvenience it is to have our infants baptized, becauſe it will intaile priviledges to us in reference to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But to theſe priviledges he ſaith, <hi>They muſt be ſanctified,</hi> quoting that place I anſwered already, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. Yet I ſay they are ſanctified or ſet apart from <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> for the Chriſtian Church; <hi>elſe were they unclean, but now they are holy,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. then they ought to be baptized. But he hath a third inconvenience, and that is, <hi>If infants be baptized, it will make a ſeparation and diſtraction in Chriſts conjunction, and that is to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize ſuch as they will not give the Lords Supper, nor admit them nor others to break Bread; Chriſt would have them to do both, and they will admit ſuch as cannot do both.</hi> But he hath no reaſon why ſome may not do ſome duties when they are diſabled to do others; and therefore I refer him to my anſwer to the tenth Objection, and hither too: for all his inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:125273:14"/>I ſee no good Argument to keep infants of Chriſtians from Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
               <p>Fifthly: He ſaith, <hi>The baptizing of infants doth directly croſſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings both in the time of the Law and in the time of the Goſpel, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ought not to be done; for they did all, both under the Law and in the time of the Gospel, by a rule; elſe</hi> Lot <hi>might have pleaded the ſame priviledge with</hi> Abraham, <hi>being a Beleever as well as he; and</hi> Iſhmael <hi>who was no Beleever in God, yet he was circumciſed.</hi> I anſwer: The promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> was, that his ſeed in <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould be the viſible Church, who onely ſhould have the token of the Covenant; and this excludes <hi>Lot</hi> from this priviledge: and for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> he being one of his Family, by vertue of another command, was circumciſed, when the Lord would have <hi>Abraham</hi> to make his own houſe an example or a patern for all his poſterity, to circumciſe in his houſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.12, 13. <hi>But,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will eſtabliſh my Covenant with</hi> Iſaac, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. Onely Strangers had this benefit by living amongſt them. So then, by the like reaſon our children (although as bad as <hi>Iſhmael</hi>) may be baptized; when as ſome true Beleevers amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> may not be baptized except they come to us and make an open profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion; then they may have this benefit amongſt us. But have not we a rule for what we do, when as the command of Chriſt is our direction, who commands all Nations to be taught and baptized? and if he command it, he will have it done, although the Anabaptiſts would bar the Chriſtian Church from that benefit to be a holy Nation, as the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was flat againſt many promiſes that whole Nations ſhould come into the Chriſtian Church, and Chriſts command to teach and baptize all Nations. But I have anſwered this in reply to Maſter <hi>Hobſon</hi>'s third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument; and ſo notwithſtanding their Objections and Arguments made againſt baptizing of Chriſtian infants, I ſee no ſufficient ground to bar them from the Ordinance of Baptiſm.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="point">
            <head>The ſecond Point is, that ſprinkling the baptized more agreeth with the minde of Christ, then dipping or plunging the baptized in or under the water.</head>
            <p>Now I come to the ſecond Point to prove that ſprinkling the baptized more agreeth to the minde of Chriſt, then dipping or plunging the baptized in or under the water:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe Baptiſm is a Sacrament or viſible ſigne to our corporall eyes, to put us in minde of the thing ſignified, as the Rainbow ſhall be ſeen in the clouds, which was the token of the Covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.11, 14. and <hi>Moſes</hi> took blood and ſprinkled it on the people and ſaid, <hi>Behold the blood of the Covenant, Exodus</hi> 24.7. But when the baptized are plunged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:125273:15"/>under water, they can neither behold the ſignes or token of the Covenant, nor hear the words of Inſtitution to put them in minde of the Covenant or thing ſignified; they cannot have their ſences exerciſed as they ought, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. becauſe their life is in danger to be loſt; and a drunken man or a mad man is as fit to make uſe of the ſigne, as a man under water, being out of his element; therefore the baptized ought not to be plunged under water.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If they ſhould ſtand on the bank and plunge the baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water, in ſo doing they may break his neck againſt the bottom, if the water be ſhallow; or if deep, they may drown him; neither date they jump in to ſave his life leſt they drown themſelves; and if they ſhould hate one in the River to catch him, then there cannot be leſſe then two to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize one man, which is contrary to all examples in Scripture. Then, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo dangerous to plunge the baptized into the water, whether it be deep or ſhallow, I would intreat them to ſhew me when there is neither too much nor too little water, to avoid theſe dangers; for till then, I ſhall hold it unlawfull to plunge the baptized in or under water.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Jaylor and all his were baptized in the night; but if they had been ſo plunged, ſure they would have either killed or drowned them; neither could they avoid it, becauſe at midnight they could not ſee their riſing; neither do I read that they jumped in to endanger their own lives to ſave them: then ſure they were not plunged into it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If they ſo plunge the baptized into the water, being naked, it is againſt modeſty; <hi>But,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, let all things be done decently,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. and ſo doing were a temptation; for <hi>David</hi> ſeeing a naked woman waſhing her ſelf, was tempted to that foul ſin of adultery, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2, 4. and Chriſt hath taught us to ſay, <hi>Lead us not into temptation, but deliver us from evil, Matth.</hi> 6. Then ſure the adminiſtration of this holy Ordinance muſt be free from ſo foul a temptation as to ſee the nakedneſſe of each other. Then it is unlawfull to plunge the baptized naked into the water.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If they have drawers for that uſe, they are ſure the holy Breeches of <hi>Aaron,</hi> as bad as the Prelates Surpleſſe; and for Women to wear them, being mans Apparel, <hi>is an abomination to the Lord, Deut.</hi> 22.5. therefore not to be plunged in drawers appointed for that uſe.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If they ſay that they were plunged in their Wearing Clothes, is more then they can prove; yea, it ſeems they were not ſo plunged in their Wearing Clothes; for when <hi>Lydia</hi> and the <hi>Jaylor</hi> were baptized, although at ſeveral times, they feaſted the Apoſtles ſtraight-way, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15, 33, 34. But we do not finde that they ſhifted themſelves either before or after that Ordinace; Then, did they ſit at meat together dung-wet as they came out of the water? If they ſay, yea, then they muſt prove it, and till then, we
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:125273:15"/>ſhall not beleeve that they were plunged into the water in their Wearing Clothes.</p>
            <p>Sevently, If they had any Clothes upon them when they were plunged into the water, then the water could not touch them all over, and ſo they had as good be ſprinkled on one place for all.</p>
            <p>Eightly, Many were baptized in their Houſes, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and others, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.17, 18. and 10.25, 48. And the <hi>Jaylor</hi> was baptized at midnight in the Priſon; But what Veſſel could theſe be ſo plunged in, and where had they ſuch a Veſtel in the Priſon, and filled with water ſo ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as to be all baptized the ſame hour, and at midnight? And what Veſſel had <hi>Peter</hi> to baptize three thouſand in ſome few hours ſpace? <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. If their Veſſel could hold but two or three together, did they empty it ſo many times? And who fetcht all that water? And it may be ſome of them were diſeaſed, and others would not be plunged in the ſame water, and ſo they emptied it three thouſand times over: But did <hi>Peter</hi> ſtand in the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel all that time, or was he in the water at all, or <hi>Ananias</hi> when he baptized <hi>Paul</hi> in the Houſe, or <hi>Peter</hi> when he baptized <hi>Cornelius</hi> in the Houſe, or <hi>Paul</hi> when he baptized the <hi>Jaylor?</hi> Till this be proved, we ſhall not beleeve that they were plunged in the water.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, The Sacraments muſt be Adminiſtred where the Word is Preached; for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Teach all Nations baptizing them, Matth.</hi> 28.19. He doth not ſay Preach in one place, and then take them to a River to plunge them: And to hold that one Ordinance alone is to be adminiſtred apart from the meeting place of the Aſſembly for all other publike duties, is ſure the Popiſh Pilgrimage, or at leaſt his going a Preceſſioning; for it was never juſtified of Chriſt, and therefore to be abhorred of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, Water is a ſigne of the <hi>Blood of Chriſt,</hi> which is called <hi>the Blood of ſprinkling,</hi> having ſprinkled our hearts from an evil conſcience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.20. and 12.24. And <hi>Moſes</hi> ſprinkled the people, and ſaid, <hi>Behold the blood of the Covenant, Exod.</hi> 24.8. And the Lord ſaith, <hi>I will ſprinkle you with clean water, and ye ſhall be clean, Ezek.</hi> 36.25. Then why ſhould not this Prophecy be fulfilled in ſprinkling the baptized? And why ſhould not the ſigne of Water reſemble the ſubſtance by ſprinkling? Therefore the baptized ought rather to be ſprinkled, then plunged into the Water; and becauſe Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If I waſh one part, thou art clean every whit, John</hi> 13, 8. Then ſprinkling and not plunging, is moſt agreeing to the minde of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I fear they do not ſo plunge the baptized as they do profeſſe, but rather let them wade into the water themſelves, and ſo themſelves bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize half their body without their help, and without any word of Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution from them, and then they come afterwards and baptize the other
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:125273:16"/>half in the name of the Trinity: But if this be their manner, they contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict their own Tenet, and condemn themſelves in ſo doing: And what ſhameful thing it is for them to report that they plunge the baptized into the Water, when as they wade in themſelves? And ſo while they judge us for baptizing one part for all, they condemn themſelves for doing the ſame thing, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1. From theſe grounds we may ſafely conclude, That ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the baptized is more agreeing to the minde of Chriſt, then to plunge the baptized into the water.</p>
            <p>But to theſe Arguments Maſter <hi>Patience</hi> ſaid ſome thing, although to ſmall purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſaith he, I take dipping to be the command of Chriſt, becauſe Maſter <hi>Daniel Rogers</hi> doth ſay That the <hi>Greek</hi> word doth ſignifie waſhing by plunging; and he ſaith, Sprinkling is rinſing, and not to baptize, as Maſter <hi>Blackwood</hi> doth prove from <hi>Greek</hi> Authors; but I then replyed ſaying, <hi>Are you a Teacher in Iſrael, and know not theſe things? John</hi> 3.10. Have you the care of ſouls committed unto you, and do you feel them by hearſay, becauſe you are not able to interpret the Word your ſelf? What is this <hi>But the blinde leads the blinds, till both fall into the ditch?</hi> And what comfort will it be to you at the day of Judgement, having ſeduced many ſouls, in giving them poyſon inſtead of wholeſome food; for you to ſay then that men told you it was good for them, when as Chriſt never told you ſo? And if we ſhould go by hearſay, we might bring multitudes of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Divines and Churches that well underſtand the Language in which Chriſt ſpake unto his Church, to witneſſe, That the word <hi>Baptize</hi> ſignifies as well <hi>Sprinkling</hi> as <hi>Plunging.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, But then he ſaid <hi>Baptiſm</hi> ſignified <hi>Burial,</hi> and putting on whole Chriſt on whole man: But this I grant, For in ſprinkling, the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized are under water, as well as in plunging; for the Miniſter holds the water over the baptized, and ſo the baptized is wholly under it; when as in plunging them into the water, it may be ſome part of them was not wholly under it: And beſides, when the Miniſter holds the water over them, it is all one as to put them under it, when as it may be the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> wade in and put themſelves half under, flat againſt their own Tenet: And then they grant, that the putting the other half into the water, is a putting on whole Chriſt: Then by the ſame Argument, by ſprinkling one part, Chriſt may be wholly put on as well as by their practiſe; and the <hi>Jews</hi> by circumciſing one part, they were circumciſed all over, and ſo put on whole Chriſt. Again, although it be ſaid Baptiſm ſaves, it is not by the outward waſhing, becauſe every part of the body was waſhed, but rather by the anſwer of a good conſcience. But this is not done by Burial, but rather by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 3.21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Then he ſaid that <hi>John Dipped</hi> in <hi>Jordan;</hi> but I may as well ſay;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:125273:16"/>he <hi>Sprinkled</hi> in <hi>Jordan;</hi> for he ſaith, <hi>I indeed baptize with water, Matth.</hi> 3.11. But the word <hi>with</hi> is not always <hi>in</hi> there; there was <hi>with</hi> the Angel a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.13. I hope you will not ſay they were in the Angel; and if I were with you, I hope you would not ſay that I were in you: So then to baptize with water may be by ſprinkling the baptized, and not by plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into the water; and to put in for <hi>with</hi> is as bad a miſtake as that of the Prelates, who would bow at the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> inſtead of <hi>In the Name of Jeſus,</hi> from that place <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10. So you will baptize with <hi>the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> inſtead of <hi>in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt:</hi> Becauſe to baptize with water, you will have it all one as to be baptized in the water, by plunging the baptized un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or into the water.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Then he ſaid, <hi>If Chriſt command to dip, then ſprinkling is but a greſſe invention of man;</hi> but then he did not prove that Chriſt did onely command to dip, and not to ſprinkle, but to baptize, which ſignifies <hi>both:</hi> Then we may ſprinkle the baptized with as good, if not better warrant, then they may plunge them into the water.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Suppoſe they ſay Chriſt came out of the water, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3 16. And it is ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> went both into the water, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hence they conclude, That the Baptized ought to be plunged into the water. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> If they waded into the water, then they were not plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into it: Neither is it ſaid that either Chriſt or the Eunuch were plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the water; neither doth their going into the water hinder but they may be ſprinkled; for in thoſe hot Countreys they went bare-foot, and it is likely they went in ſome diſtance from the ſide, that they might come at clear water, and then both <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> might ſprinkle them <hi>In the Name of the Trinity:</hi> And I think the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have nothing to ſay from Scripture or Reaſon againſt it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall: here conclude with one Quere, which is this, <hi>If our Miniſters be lawfully ſent and authorized from Chriſt, and the Presbytery, to Preach and Baptize, and they do adminiſter this Ordinance of Baptiſm in the right Form</hi> In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, <hi>and with the right Matter, being Water, and on the right Parties, being either men of yeers when they are converted to the</hi> Chriſtian Religion, <hi>or to Infants born of Chriſtians; and to the right end, which is to diſtinguiſh them from Turks and Infidels, and as an engagement to us all to go on in obedience of the true</hi> Chriſtian Religion: <hi>And laſtly, That Chriſt ſhould ratifie that outward Form of Baptiſm according as</hi> John <hi>the</hi> Baptiſt <hi>foretold, and baptized them</hi> with the Holy Ghoſt,</p>
            <p>I would know this of the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> how they dare to renounce this outward Form of Baptiſm thus rightly adminiſtred in our Church, and ratified by the Holy Ghoſt, and all becauſe it was done upon them when
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:125273:17"/>they were Infants; therefore the very Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; or it may be becauſe they were not plunged into the water, Therefore the outward Form and the inward Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt is deſpiſed of them; when as they may ſee the vanity of plunging by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forementioned Arguments againſt it. But will they caſt away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> outward and inward Seal and Token of the Covenant, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by perſons lawfully called to do it, who do it in the right Form, on the right Parties, with the right Matter, and to the right end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> confirmed by the Holy Ghoſt as by a faithful witneſſe that cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e? But will they diſpiſe the Baptiſm of the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe it was do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upon Infants, or becauſe they were ſprinkled and not plunged into the water? And ſo like Witches renounce the Covenant of Grace, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> away both the outward and inward Seals of it, when they enter into Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Divel; ſo theſe people, it is to be feared, many of them do commit that unpardonable ſin, when they turn <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> deſpiſing and trampling under feet the Spirit of God, whereby they <hi>ſhould be S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>led to the day of Redemption;</hi> For commonly they go on in a final <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and not one of Ten thouſand ever returns; yea, many of them in theſe days are ran ſo far from God, that they do not beleeve that there is either God or Devil, Heaven or Hell, Church of Grace or Glory; Thus they are now faln to notorious Atheiſm, calling themſelves <hi>Seckers</hi> of the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned things, which for the preſent they have loſt.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
